Association of Collegiate Alumnae records SSC.MS.00325
Sophia Smith Collection
Association of Collegiate Alumnae records
1882-1921
Sophia Smith Collection
Association of Collegiate Alumnae (U.S.)--History--Sources
SSC.MS.00325
2.396 linear feet (4 containers)
The Association of Collegiate Alumnae was formed in Boston in 1882 to unite women graduates of four-year colleges and universities around issues including standards of academic programs, isolation following the college experience, living wage for college alumnae and concerns about their place in the academy. These records contain reports, correspondence, announcements, publications, registers, and a scrapbook on topics relating to the education of women in the late 19th century, medical education of women, athletics for women wages of working women, and school lunch programs.
Biographical / Historical
In 1882 Marion Talbot, Alice Freeman Palmer, Alice Hayes, Ellen Swallow Richards, and thirteen other women met in Boston to establish the Association of Collegiate Alumnae (ACA), uniting college graduates for "practical educational work." Members of the first generation of college-educated women, they had struggled to get an education only to find that society had no place for them and no interest in utilizing their abilities. Through the new organization (ACA), they hoped to promote and raise standards for women's higher education. To distinguish themselves from normal-school and academy graduates, they limited membership to alumnae of specified, carefully selected four-year colleges and universities. Additionally, they expected the ACA to help end the social isolation often faced by women college graduates when they returned home. Women in other regions responded enthusiastically and set up ACA branches across the country. Founded in 1901, the Southern Association of College Women (SACW) served a similar community. In 1921 the ACA and the SACW merged, forming the American Association of University Women (AAUW). Although the ACA, the SACW, and later the AAUW were committed to equal access to education, they avoided identification as explicitly feminist organizations. Until the 1970s, AAUW leaders rejected controversial and potentially divisive issues like suffrage and the Equal Rights Amendment.
During its first fifty years, the ACA studied a variety of issues related to women's education. Its members addressed the status of women within the academy by lobbying for women to serve as college trustees, fought discrimination on coeducational campuses, and argued for inclusion in the curriculum of home economics courses designed to make homemaking more professional and scientific. Additionally, the ACA provided fellowships for undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral study, and encouraged women's careers, particularly in the social sciences. Activities of regional branches and local groups of the ACA varied. The internationalism of the war years carried over into the 1920s, when the AAUW joined similar organizations from eight other countries to promote women's education around the world and to create an international community of college women through the International Federation of College Women.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Association of Collegiate Alumnae include announcements, registers, copies of the A.C.A. Journal (1918), a scrapbook, and committee, financial, and branch reports. The records also contain correspondence relating to living wage of college women and accompanying investigations, including letters to Ellen Richards and to internationalist and pacifist Fannie Fern Andrews. Pamphlets of special interest concern the medical education of women, college entrance requirements, history of the A.C.A., Domestic Reform League, comparative statistics on colleges, university extension programs, alumnae gifts, athletics for women, wages of working women, school lunch programs, and a bibliography on higher education of women.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--History--Sources; Women college graduates--United States--History--Sources; Women--Education--United States--History--Sources; Publications; Women--Employment--United States--History-Sources; Photographs.; correspondence; reports; Constitutions; clippings; American Association of University Women--History--Sources; Association of Collegiate Alumnae; unknown; Association of Collegiate Alumnae
- Announcements of meetings, financial reports, miscellaneous reports, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Constitution, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Organizational reports, 1892-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bureau of Occupations, 1892-1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1892-1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Quarter-centennial scrapbook, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Branches
  - Boston
    - Constitution and members materials (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Publications, 1891-1916 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Quartercenntenial meeting, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pamphlets, general (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - California (Box 2, Box 12)
  - New York (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Philadelphia (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Committees; reports and correspondence
  - Living wage
    - Committee reports (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Committee reports, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    - Questionnaires and returns (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Studies, notes, and publicity (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Study and development of children (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Corporate Membership (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Finance and Publication (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Graduate Study (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Health Statistics (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - National University (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Physical Education (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Reorganization (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Standards (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Vocational Opportunities (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Correspondence
  - Andrews, Fannie Fern, 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Papers
  - Contents of papers in bound volume (Box 3)
  - Series II (not included in bound volume) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Publications not in series (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Series III (reprints) (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - ACA papers and National University
    - ACA Registers, 1884-1898 (Box 4)
    - ACA Publications, Series 3, 1-22, with Register, 1898-1910; 1899-1909 (Box 4)
    - ACA Journal (AAUW Journal), v. 4-14, (6v), 1911-1921 (Box 4)